Preliminary Guide to the John Clayton Tracy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Clayton Tracy papers
1892-1952
MS 502
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The John Clayton Tracy Papers consist of writings, correspondence, and subject files relating to Tracy's role as professor of civil engineering and head of the Department of Civil Engineering at the Sheffield Scientific School, secretary of the Yale Class of 1890 (S.S.S.), and Yale representative to the Society of Sigma Xi.
Tracy, John C. (John Clayton), 1869-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Carleton Smith and the Department of Civil Engineering, Yale University.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John Clayton Tracy, civil engineer and author, was born in Willimantic, Connecticut on November 3, 1869. He received his Ph.B. from the Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, in 1890, and his C.E. in 1892. Tracy was an instructor (1891-1892), assistant professor (1902-1915), and professor (1915-1936) in the Department of Civil Engineering at Yale. He also served as department chairman from 1915-1936.
Member of the Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, Connecticut Society of Civil Engineers, Graduates Club. Director of the New Haven Chamber of Commerce, Member Executive Committee Yale Engineering Association, Yale representative on the national council of the Society of the Sigma Xi.
Tracy died on November 1, 1955.
Scope and Contents
The John Clayton Tracy Papers consist of writings, correspondence, and subject files relating to Tracy's role as professor of civil engineering and head of the Department of Civil Engineering at the Sheffield Scientific School, secretary of the Yale Class of 1890 (S.S.S.), and Yale representative to the Society of Sigma Xi.
Civil engineering -- United States; Engineering -- Study and teaching -- United States; Educators; Engineers; Tracy, John C. (John Clayton), 1869-1955; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. School of Engineering
- Inventory
  - Writings
    - [Surveying; Theory and Practice or Plane Surveying?]: drafts and related papers, [1903-1947?] (Box 1-3)
    - "Bridge Building": two notebooks, 1892 (Box 4)
    - [Copies of various speeches or papers?], 1905, 1911, undated (Box 5)
    - Plane Surveying: A Text Book and Pocket Manual, 1907 (Box 5)
    - Exercises in Surveying, 1909 (Box 5)
    - Descriptive Geometry: page proofs, [1914?] (Box 5)
    - Stresses Statically Determined
      - [Draft of letter to McGraw Hill Co. about book?], advertisements, 1922 September 8, [1929?] (Box 5)
      - Proofs, 1929 (Box 5)
      - Editorial and reader correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 5)
    - "Permissible Errors in Measurements on Running Tracks," related correspondence, 1937, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous biographical sketches, miscellaneous papers, 1943, undated (Box 5)
    - "Talk to the Graduating Class of Civil Engineers", 1952 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous printed geometric figures, undated (Box 5)
    - "Notes for Lecture on the Panama Canal," miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 5)
  - Sigma Xi
    - Printed matter, 1898-1915, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, Circa 1902-1907 (Box 6)
    - Nomination blanks, miscellaneous cards, 1902, 1903, 1905, 1908, undated (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers, [1902-1914?] (Box 6)
  - Class of 1890S
    - "Class [of] 1890S correspondence", Circa 1920-1928 (Box 6)
    - "Records of the Class: 1890S", 1925 (Box 6)
    - "Replies to (90S) Questionnaires", 1925, 1930 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1926-1938, undated (Box 7)
    - "Class [of] 1890S: correspondence", Circa 1928-1931 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence of Tracy as Class Secretary, Circa 1928-1935, 1952, 1954 (Box 7)
    - "Class of 90S: Letters (1930)" (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, two class buttons, Circa 1930-1942 (Box 7)
    - "90S correspondence, 1931-1932" (Box 8)
    - Papers relating to the forty-fifth reunion, 1935 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous letters, [ca. 1940-1950?] (Box 8)
    - "Class Notes, Alumni Magazine, including notices of deaths", [1949, 1950, 1951?] (Box 8)
    - "Class Record, Death of Heyworth", [1951?] (Box 8)
  - Yale University and Engineering
    - Papers on engineering education, miscellaneous papers, Circa 1900-1923, undated (Box 9)
    - "Discussion of engineering problems at Yale," miscellaneous papers, [1905-1920?] (Box 9)
    - Blueprint of Yale Athletic Field, [1912?] (Box 9)
    - "Committee of Twenty-one and the 'Bowl'", Circa 1913 (Box 9)
    - "Intra departmental engineering discussion," miscellaneous papers, 1915, undated (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous papers, Circa 1915-1923, undated (Box 9)
    - "University Reorganization", 1918, undated (Box 9)
    - "Correspondence 1919: Transmission and Communication Electro-Physics" (Box 9)
    - "Engineering Degrees", 1919, undated (Box 9)
    - "Freshman Engineering", undated (Box 9)
    - "Transportation and Administrative Engineering", 1919, 1920 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1919, 1921, undated (Box 10)
    - "ROTC., 1919-1921" (Box 10)
    - ["Graduate School"?], 1919-1922, undated (Box 10)
    - "Plans for the Development of the Engineering Departmentat Yale University", 1920 (Box 10)
    - John C. Tracy: "'Notes on Bridge Design'...prepared for the use of the students...", undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellany
    - Papers and letters related to the Red Cross, Circa 1928-1932 (Box 10)
    - Papers concerning the Tracy Memorial Tablet, miscellaneous papers, 1915, 1939, 1943 (Box 10)